Gladys Virginia Swackhamer Papers, 1881-1988
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Gladys V. Swackhamer papers
1881-1988
1900-1988
Swackhamer, Gladys V.
MS 268
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Pacifist; psychiatric social worker; and political activist. The collection documents topics such as conscientious objector status during the Vietnam War; nuclear disarmament; the environment; homelessness; the plight of migrant farm workers; and governmental waste and mismanagement; as well as her work with the WPA and other agencies. Materials include photographs; correspondence; and unpublished autobiographical writings, including recordings and interpretations of her dreams.
Gladys Virginia Swackhamer was born September 17, 1893 in Hagerstown, Maryland, the daughter of Judge Austin H. Swackhamer and Florence Anderson Swackhamer. She received her Bachelor of Arts Degree from Smith College in 1917 and went on to earn her Master of Social Work in 1923 as a member of the first class of the Smith College School for Social Work. She then obtained a Certificate of Proficiency in the German language from the Institut fuer Auslaender at the University of Berlin.
Early in her professional career, Swackhamer practiced social case work in hospitals and clinics in Pennsylvania, New Jersey and New York. After obtaining a position as Secretary and Research Assistant to the editor of the Psychoanalytic Quarterly in 1927, her professional interests evolved in the direction of research and writing. From 1933 through 1945, she conducted "psychiatric, medical and industrial research for private and government agencies". Cigar Makers After the Lay-Off, 1937, a WPA project, evaluated the problem of workers' welfare following termination of employment due to industrial mechanization, and Choice and Change of Doctors, 1939, examined how low-income families and individuals exercised freedom of choice in selecting medical care. In 1945 Swackhamer resumed practicing social work, continuing until her retirement in 1957 (having moved to Santa Barbara, California in 1949). In addition to writing articles and abstracts for professional journals, she also translated into English the work of several German scholars.
Upon retirement, Swackhamer continued her life-long involvement in the Unitarian Church and also pursued a variety of community interests, including the League of Women Voters, the Sierra Club, and the Child Guidance Clinic of Santa Barbara. She was a committed pacifist and took great interest in the political issues of her day, frequently writing articulate, well-informed letters to her elected representatives and to the editors of local newspapers. In 1986, under the aegis of the Nuclear Age Peace Foundation, Swackhamer initiated the Austin H. and Florence A. Swackhamer Memorial Prizes, to be awarded annually to three college-bound high school seniors for the best essays on how to promote world peace in the nuclear age. The contest was open to international and United States students, and the essays were to focus on specific themes, determined each year by Swackhamer and the staff of the Nuclear Age Peace Foundation.
Swackhamer was listed in Who's Who of American Women (5th edition, 1969), and in 1970 was made a life fellow of the American Orthopsychiatric Association. She died in Santa Barbara, California on September 6, 1988.
The collection is comprised of biographical material, genealogical records, photographs, correspondence, writings, material pertaining to professional activities, and subject files. Obituaries and condolences for Swackhamer's father, a prominent New Jersey judge, are also included. Personal correspondence is extensive, most notably letters between Swackhamer and her maternal uncle, C.W.G. Anderson, spanning a period of forty years. There is a significant amount of genealogical material as well. Also of potential interest is correspondence with Richard Clemmer, which documents his effort to obtain conscientious objector status during the Vietnam War.
There is also material pertaining to social and political activism in the 1980s, including Swackhamer's letters to editors of newspapers and to her elected representatives on such topics as nuclear disarmament, the environment, homelessness, the plight of migrant farm workers, and governmental waste and mismanagement.
Towards the end of her life Swackhamer began attending writing classes taught by a local author, Robert Downey, resulting in short, descriptive narratives that were autobiographical in nature. She also began recording and interpreting her dreams.
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biographical
II. Photographs
III. Correspondence
IV. Professional Activities
V. Writings
VI. Subjects
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Roberta Weissglass donated the Gladys Virginia Swackhamer Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1990.
Search Terms
Antinuclear movement--United States--History--Sources; Jelliffe, Smith Ely, 1866-1945; Migrant labor--United States--History--Sources; United States. Work Projects Administration--History; Unemployed--United States--Case Studies; Psychiatric social work--United States--History--Sources; Smith College. School for Social Work.--History--Sources; Social workers--United States--History; Swackhamer, Gladys V.; Swackhamer, Austin H; Environmental protection--Citizen participation--History--20th century--Sources; Industrial hygiene--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL 1901-88, 5 linear in.
  Resumes, educational records, obituaries, legal documents, genealogical material, travel memorabilia, address books.
- SERIES II. PHOTOGRAPHS 1903-29, undated, 1 linear in.
  Portraits of Gladys Virginia Swackhamer; some of immediate family.
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1900-86, 6 linear in.
  Personal, professional and political correspondence.
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1929-88, 4 linear in.
  Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and journal article.
- SERIES V. WRITINGS 1937-86, 3 linear in.
  Reports, surveys, studies and journal articles, creative writing pieces, records and interpretation of dreams.
- SERIES VI. SUBJECTS 1930, undated, .5 linear in.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL 1901-88
  - Obituary, memorials, curriculum vitae, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Education
    - Primary and secondary school memorabilia, 1901, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Smith College, 1913, 1917-18, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Smith College School for Social Work, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Smith College Reunion & Smith College news, 1966-86 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Who's Who of American Women, 1966, 1968, 1970-74, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Valley Verde Retirement Community, 1984-87 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Living Will and funeral arrangements, 1975-81, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Travel, 1920-32, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Address books, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Genealogy
    - Family tree and other documentation, 1876-82 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence about genealogy with Mish, Mary, 1962-63, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Swackhamer, Austin, 1856-1943
      - Obituaries and condolences, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Memorabilia, 1881-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Swackhamer, Florence (1860-1955): Correspondence and memorabilia, 1873-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Swackhamer, Donald (1890-1959): Correspondence, memorials and miscellany, 1931, 1975, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Swackhamer, Samuel S.: Correspondence, clippings, 1883, 1911, 1947, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Swackhamer, C. G. W. (1863-1952): Last will and testament, biographical information and memorabilia, 1855-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Anderson, George: Correspondence and memorabilia, 1876-78, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-50, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- SERIES II. PHOTOGRAPHS 1903-29, undated
  - Portraits of Gladys Virginia Swackhamer, 1903, 1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Portraits of family members, and miscellaneous photographs, 1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1900-86
  - Personal
    - Family
      - General, 1900, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Florence A. Swackhamer, 1912-46, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
      - C.V.G. Anderson, 1910-52, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
      - Jones, Jinny, 1978-84 (Box 2, Folder 27a)
      - Meyers, Sarah, 1946-74 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Newcomer, Charlotte, 1946-82 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Friends
      - General, 1920-45 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - General, 1946-84, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Beckham, Edward, 1932-50, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Bisbee, George A., 1922-49, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Clemmer, Richard, 1960-84, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - {no folder 35} (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Lawrence, Waterbury, 1934, 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Kartzke, Georg, 1946-85 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Kates, Arnold, 1939-50, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Kiefer, Felix, 1947-51 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Foreign, 1929-83, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Christmas cards, 1931-56, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Professional
    - General, 1918-66, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Letter of recommendation, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Political
    - To newspaper editors, 1954-86 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - To elected representatives, 1963-86, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - To Chavez, Cesar (United Farm Workers), 1984-85 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Immigration, 1938-39, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1929-88
  - Committee on Research in Medical Economics, 1938-40 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - International Conference of Social Work, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Nuclear Age Peace Foundation, 1984-88, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - German translations
    - Correspondence, 1929-56, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "Psychoanalytic Experiences in Public School Practice," by Hans Zullinger, 1940-41 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- SERIES V. WRITINGS 1937-86
  - Reports, surveys and studies
    - "Survey of the Relief Population of the Municipalities of Clayton, Franklin Township, Monroe Township and Newfield in Gloucester County, New Jersey," 1935 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Cigar Makers After the Lay-off"
      - Published manuscript and press release, 1937-38 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Correspondence, 1938-39, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "Choice and Change of Doctors"
      - Published manuscript, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Correspondence, 1939-40, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - Reviews, press releases and related material, 1939-40, 1945, 1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "Some Factors in Maintaining Contact With Clinic Patients," 1941 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Journal articles
    - " Any Sickness in The Family?," 1938 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - " Towards Industrial & Mental Health," 1947 (Box 4)
    - "Imago"
      - Abstracts, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Correspondence with Smith Ely Jelliffe, 1930-37 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Smith Ely Jelliffe: Obituary and journal articles, 1937, 1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Unpublished works
    - Lecture, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Journal articles, 1938, 1940-41, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Creative writing class with Robert Downey, 1982-84, undated (Box 4, Folder 66-67)
    - Dreams, 1983-86, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Position paper: "The Farm Worker," undated (Box 4, Folder 69-70)
- SERIES VI. SUBJECTS 1930, undated
  - Mental health, 1930, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Politics, 1928, 1960-64, 1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL
  - Photographs of Gladys Virginia Swackhamer and Austin H. Swackhamer, undated (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Award of Merit, Valley Verde Retirement Community, undated (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Family tree, undated (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Appeal to the House of Representatives to abolish the House Unamerican Activities Committee, New York Times, 22 Feb 1962 (Map-case Flat File:)